Finding Aid for the Jack Allen Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Jack Allen Collection
2014
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0650
5 linear feet
Biographical Note
Jack Allen was born in 1914 in Prestonsburg, Kentucky to Anna Mayo Allen and Edward Allen. Jack Allen attended school in Prestonsburg and graduated high school in 1931. After high school he attended Eastern Kentucky State Teachers College where he received his A.B. in 1935. After teaching high school for two years in Prestonsburg Allen left for Nashville, Tennessee to attended graduate school at George Peabody College. He graduated with a doctoral degree in 1941 and took a job at his alma mater, Eastern Kentucky State Teachers College.
Jack met Peabody coed Cherry Falls in 1940 and married her in August 1941. He entered the Navy in August of 1942 and was assigned to Dallas, Texas on a Naval Selection Board. By 1943 he had reached the rank of Ensign and was re-assigned to Pearl Harbor, Hawaii. In Hawaii he was placed with the Pacific Fleet Radar Center. He was released from duty in 1945 and took a job with George Peabody College in 1946 where he remained for 33 years.
Allen served on many boards and committees through the years including the National Council for the Social Studies where he was especially active in shaping the teaching of social studies to high school students. He also authored 15 textbooks and co-authored another 20 with colleagues.
He and Cherry had three sons David, Robert, and Edward. Jack Allen passed away on June 19, 2004 at the age of 89.
Scope and Content
The Jack Allen Collection is an accumulation of Allen’s productive life as an educator at George Peabody College for Teachers in Nashville, Tennessee. The collection comprises five linear feet (4 Paige boxes) relating to Jack Allen’s career and writings.
Only a few letters appear in the papers though the three from Jack Allen to his mother written in 1961 discuss his life in South Korea while on assignment from George Peabody College. Other items of interest are his writings on the teaching of Social Studies in high schools and primary grades.
Making up ¾ of the collection are textbooks which Allen wrote or co-wrote with colleagues. These textbooks trace the career of Jack Allen from 1949 to 1982 and are indicative of the progression of styles of social studies textbooks created for schools during those periods.
The Jack Allen Collection was donated to Special Collections in 2007 by his widow Cherry Allen of Nashville, Tennessee.
- Box Listing
  - Folder
    - Correspondence –Outgoing to Mother, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence –General, 1974, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Biographical Information –“My Philosophy of Living” by Jack Allen, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Biographical Information –“And So I Became a Teacher” by Jack Allen (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Biographical Information –“My Century –The Early Years” by Jack Allen, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Biographical Information –“My Century –The Later Years” by Jack Allen, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Biographical Information –Newspaper Clippings of Jack Allen (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Biographical Information –Oral History Project at University of Texas (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Education –Notebook from George Peabody College for Teachers (GPCT) Economics 440 Economics and Geography (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Education –Notebook GPCT Education 420b History of Education (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Education –Notebook GPCT Education 471 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Education –Notebook GPCT Education 526 History of Philosophy/Education (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Education –Notebook GPCT Education 689 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Education –Notebook GPCT History 410 Revolutionary Period (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Education –Notebook GPCT History 413 19th century Europe (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Education –Notebook GPCT History 426 American Sectional Controversies (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Education –Notebook GPCT History 473 Essay (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Education –Notebook GPCT History 475 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Education –Notebook GPCT History 540 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Education –Notebook GPCT Sociology 531 Social Problems of the Southern Regions (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Education – Master of Arts Thesis “Grade Placement of History”, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Education –Introduction to doctoral dissertation “The Diary of Randal William McGavock, 1852-1862” (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Career –George Peabody College (GPC) activities (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Career –Meetings and Awards (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Writings –As Jack Allen Sees Henry Hill (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Writings –Curriculum Planning in American Schools: The Social Studies, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Writings –Life in a Global Village (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Writings –Old Oak Club (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Writings –Peabody Saga, article (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Writings –Textbooks for Schools and Colleges –A talk to Nashville Librarians on, October 4, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Writings –Thoughts on the future of Social Studies (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Writings –Tribute to John E. Windrow, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Writings –“The Community and Social Understanding” in The Council Courier, December 1941, p.3 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Writings –“Readers Comments on “What is Needed”” in Social Education: Official Journal, National Council for the Social Studies, Vol.12 no.5, May 1948, p.198 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Writings –“Review of Readings in American Educational History” in the Journal of Southern History, November 1951, p.570-571 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Writings –“The Modern Social Studies Teacher –a Portrait” in NEA Journal, November 1952, p.509 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Writings –“Charting Ninth Grade Social Studies” in Social Education, Vol.20 no.2, February 1956, p.68 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Writings –“The Study of Religion in High School American History” in Religious Education, July-August 1957, p.282 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Writings –“A Forward look in teaching the Social Studies” in Midland Schools: Official Publication of the Iowa Education Association, November 1958, p. 14-15 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Writings –“The Social Studies in American Schools: A Report” in The Tennessee Teacher, February 1959, p. 10-12 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Writings –“Social Studies for America’s Children” in Phi Delta Kappan, April 1959, p. 277-280 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Writings –“Of Teaching and Social Intelligence” in Social Education, Vol. 23 no.5, May 1959 p. 199-202 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Writings –“The Role of Ninth Grade Civics in Citizenship Education” in the High School Journal, Vol. 44 no. 3, December 1960, p.106-111 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Writings –“Assessing Recent Developments in the Social Studies” in Social Education, Vol. 31 no.2, February 1967, p.99-103 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Writings –“Corporate Expansion and Social Studies Textbooks” in Social Education, Vol.33 no. 3, March 1969, p.287-291 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Writings –Issues Today-Teacher’s Edition, Vol.2 no. 15, April 1, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Writings –“Response of 25 former Presidents of NCSS” in Social Education, Vol.34 no.8, November 1970, p.808 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Writings –“Asia Revisited: Fading Stereotypes” in Issues Today-Teacher’s Edition, Vol.3 no.2, September 25, 1970, p.1 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Writings –“Dissent in the Classroom” in Issues Today-Teacher’s Edition, Vol.5 no.9, February 9, 1973 Section 1, p.1 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Writings –“In My Opinion” in Council of Supervisors and Administrators of the City of New York, Vol.14 no.14, March 28, 1981, p.8-9 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Writings –“Social Studies Perspectives for the 80’s” in Close-Up on Economic & Social Studies Education. Peabody Center for Economic and Social Studies Education of Vanderbilt University, Fall, 1981, p.1-2 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Writings –“Tribute to Merrill Hartshorn, NCSS Executive Secretary, Emeritus” in Social Education, Vol. 49 no.8., November/December 1985 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Writings –“Educational Excellence: An Enduring American Tradition” in The Master Educator, Winter, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Reel-to-reel tapes “Citizenship Forum” by Jack Allen and Forrest E. Conner, Unidentified, Program #3 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Reel-to-reel tapes “Citizenship Forum” by Jack Allen and Forrest E. Conner, Program #4 Program #5 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Reel-to-reel tapes “Citizenship Forum” by Jack Allen and Forrest E. Conner, Program #6 Program #7 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Records -45’s “News Record” by Jack Allen and Forrest E. Conner, Vol. 1 nos.1-5, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Records -45’s “News Record” by Jack Allen and Forrest E. Conner, Vol.2 nos.1-9, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Records -45’s “News Record” by Jack Allen and Forrest E. Conner, Vol.3 nos.1-10, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Textbooks
    - Recent Events in the Development of America by Fremont P. Wirth. American Book Company, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Recent Events by Jack Allen and Fremont P. Wirth. American Book Company, 1949. Three copies (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Recent Events by Jack Allen and Fremont P. Wirth. American Book Company, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Recent Events by Jack Allen and Fremont P. Wirth. American Book Company, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Recent Events by Jack Allen and Fremont P. Wirth. American Book Company, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Recent Events by Jack Allen and Fremont P. Wirth. American Book Company, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Recent Events in the United States and the World by Jack Allen and Fremont P. Wirth. American Book Company, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Recent Events in the United States and the World by Jack Allen and Fremont P. Wirth. American Book Company, 1955. Two copies (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Recent Events in the United States and the World by Jack Allen and Fremont P. Wirth. American Book Company, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Recent Events in the United States and the World by Jack Allen and Fremont P. Wirth. American Book Company, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Recent Events in the United States and the World by Jack Allen and Fremont P. Wirth. American Book Company, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Recent Events in the United States and the World by Jack Allen and Fremont P. Wirth. American Book Company, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - United States History by Fremont P. Wirth. American Book Company, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - United States History –Teacher’s Manual by Jack Allen, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Workbook for United States History, revised edition by Fremont P. Wirth and Jack Allen, 1949, 1952, and 1955 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Civics by Jack Allen and Clarence Stegmier, American Book Company, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Teachers Manual and Key for Civics-50 States Edition by Jack Allen and Clarence Stegmier, American Book Company, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Workbook for Civics by Jack Allen and Clarence Stegmier, American Book Company, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - The Development of America by Fremont P. Wirth, American Book Company, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - The Development of America –Teacher’s Manual by Fremont P. Wirth and Jack Allen, American Book Company, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - The Study of Religion in the Public Schools –An Appraisal Jack Allen, contributor. American Council on Education, Washington DC, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - World History: Guide and Selected Resource Units –Phoenix Union High Schools and Phoenix College System. Jack Allen, Director. Phoenix, Arizona, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - United States History, revised edition by Fremont P. Wirth. American Book Company, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - United States History, revised edition –Teacher’s Manual by Fremont P. Wirth and Jack Allen. American Book Company, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - The Problems and Promise of American Democracy. McGraw-Hill Book Company, 1964 Prospectus (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - The Problems and Promise of American Democracy. McGraw-Hill Book Company, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - The United States of America by Jack Allen and Adelene E. Howland. Prentice-Hall Inc., 1964 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Nations Around the Globe by Jack Allen and Adelene E. Howland. Prentice-Hall Inc., 1966 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Viewpoints: USA by Bernard Feder, consultant Jack Allen. American Book Company, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Viewpoints: USA Teacher’s Edition by Bernard Feder, consultant Jack Allen. American Book Company, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - History: USA by Jack Allen and John L. Betts. American Book Company, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - History: USA Teacher’s Annotated Edition by Jack Allen and John L. Betts. American Book Company, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - This Government of Ours, a prospectus, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Textbooks
    - Contemporary Issues in American Society, Eaglton Institute, second edition. Webster Division, McGraw-Hill Book Company, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Contemporary Issues in American Society –Teacher’s Edition, prepared by Jack Allen and Russell Farnen. Webster Division, McGraw-Hill Book Company, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - The American Public School by Jack Allen. McGraw-Hill Book Company, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - USA: History with Documents, prospectus. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - USA: History with Documents, Vol. 1 by Jack Allen and John L. Betts. American Book Company, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - USA: History with Documents –Teacher’s Annotated Edition Vol.1 by Jack Allen and John L. Betts. American Book Company, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - USA: History with Documents, Vol. 2 by Jack Allen and John L. Betts. American Book Company, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - USA: History with Documents –Teachers Annotated Edition Vol. 2 by Jack Allen and John L. Betts. American Book Company, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Political and Economic Life in Planetary Society by Jack Allen. American Book Company, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Economic Life in Modern America-Teacher’s Annotated Edition by Jack Allen, Thomas H. DeBolt and Susan E. DeBolt. American Book Company, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Government and Society in Urban America –Teacher’s Annotated Edition by Jack Allen, Thomas H. DeBolt and Susan E. DeBolt. American Book Company, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - History: USA Bicentennial Edition –Teacher’s Guide by John L. Betts, American Book Company, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - One Nation Indivisible, 1777-1977: An Analysis of Unity Throughout American History. Jack Allen, Editor. Great American Achievements Program. Study Kit. Bicentennial Council of the 13 Original States Fund Inc., 1978 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - A New Republic Among Nations. Users Guide by Dana G. Kuffman. Great Achievements Program. Bicentennial Council of the 13 Original States Fund Inc., 1978 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Democracy’s Beacon: The United States in Word Affairs. Production script 3rd draft. Based on Jack Allen’s essay. Great Achievements Program. Bicentennial Council of the 13 Original States Fund Inc., University of Georgia. (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - American Society by Jack Allen. Prospectus, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - American Society Workbook by Kenneth Hilton. American Book Company, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - American Society Chapter Tests. American Book Company, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - American Book Social Studies, Prospectus, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - American Book Social Studies: Americans by Jack Allen. American Book Company, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - American Book Social Studies: Americans –Teacher’s Edition by Jack Allen. American Book Company, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - American Book Social Studies Workbook, Level E by George T. Munyan. American Book Company, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - American Book Social Studies Workbook, Level E –Teacher’s Edition by George T. Munyan. American Book Company, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - One Nation Indivisible, 1777-1977: An Analysis of Unity Throughout American History by Jack Allen. Great American Achievements Program. Bicentennial Council of the 13 Original States Fund Inc., 1979 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - A New Republic Among Nations: The Role of the United States in Foreign Affairs by Jack Allen. Great American Achievements Program. Bicentennial Council of the 13 Original States Fund Inc., 1980 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Of, By, and For the People: Sovereignty in American History by Jack Allen. Great American Achievements Program. Bicentennial Council of the 13 Original States Fund Inc., 1980 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Education in the 80’s: Social Studies Jack Allen, Editor. NEA: Washington DC, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Textbooks
    - Places-Teacher’s Edition. American Book Social Studies, American Book Company, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - The American People by Jack Allen, American Book Company, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - The American People –Teacher’s Edition by Jack Allen. American Book Company, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - The American People –Tests, Grade 5. American Book Company, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - The American People –Teacher’s Annotated Edition Workbook by George T. Munyan and Ronald Wheeler. American Book Company, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Neighbors by Dorothy J. Skeel. American Book Company, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Neighbors –Teacher’s Edition by Dorothy J. Skeel. American Book Company, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - People of the World by David C. King. American Book Company, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - People of the World –Teacher’s Edition by David C. King. American Book Company, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - People in Places by David C. King, Jay L. Weisman, and Ronald Wheeler. American Book Company, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - People in Places –Teachers Edition. American Book Company, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - People by Dorothy J. Skeel. American Book Company, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - People –Teacher’s Edition by Dorothy J. Skeel. American Book Company, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Communities-Teacher’s Edition. American Book Company, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 14)